http://youtu.be/IQiDvN0d5Vk
Ngô Thiện 1/11/2016
hello again and welcome back to operation management. In this supplemental lecture, we're gonna be taking about process throughput, try to figure out what controls the rate of units going through a particular process.
chào mừng các bạn trở lại với khóa học quản trị vận hành. Trong bài bổ trợ này, ta sẽ nói về thông lượng quá trình, chỉ ra những gì chi phối tỉ lệ của các đơn vị xuyên suốt một quá trình nào đó.
So we're gonna particularly look at the arrival rate of the unit vs process rate itself. Won't you remember what we've talked about what is the average throughput rate? We know that it is the average number of units that flow through the process in a specified period of time. So for example, it could be 10 units per hour, 50 units per day
Ta sẽ xem xét tỉ lệ đến tốc độ đến của đơn vị và tốc đọ xử lý nó. Bạn có nhớ là ta đã nói đến tốc độ lưu thông trung bình là gì không? Chúng ta đã biết đó chính là số lượng trung bình các đơn vị được đưa vào xư lý trong một khoảng thời gian cụ thể. Chẳng hạn như 10 đơn vị mỗi giờ, 50 đơn vị mỗi ngày.
12 units per minute, 100 per week, 100 per hour, 3 per second and so forth. So we're looking at units per period of time. So what affects the throughput. As i said earlier, it is
12 đơn vị mỗi phút, 100 đơn vị mỗi tuần, 3 mỗi giây v.v... Chúng ta sẽ xem xét các đơn vị mỗi khoảng thời gian. Vậy thì cái gì tác động đến thông lượng. Như tôi đã nói từ đầu, nó là
the arrival rate, which is how many units that arrive and enter the process, and it also affects the private process rate, which is how many units can be processed. So again we're looking at units per period of time. Now, there're 3 different situations. One is the arrival rate can exceed the process rate.
tốc độ đến, tức là có bao nhiêu đơn vị đến và đi vào một quá trình, và nó cũng tác động đến tốc độ xử lý riêng, tức là có bao nhiều đơn vị được xử lý. Một lần nữa chúng ta sẽ xem xét các đơn vị mỗi khoảng thời gian. Bây giời có 3 trường hợp khác nhau. Một là tốc độ đến vượt tốc độ xử lý
In this case, there are more units arrive in than the process can handle.
Trong trường hợp này, đơn vị đến sẽ nhiều hơn đơn vị có thể xử lý được
The second situation is that the arrival rate is less than the process rate, which means the process is capable of handling more units than all the arrive in. And the third situation is when the arrival rate is equal to the process rate. We're going through each of these situation independently.
Trường hơp 2 là tốc độ đến thấp hơn tốc độ xử lý, nghĩa là quá trình có thể xử lý nhiều hơn số lượng đơn vị đến. Và trường hợp 3 là khi tốc độ đến bằng tốc độ xử lý. Chúng ta sẽ xem xét những trường hợp này một cách độc lập.
In the first on, when the arrival rate exceed that of a process rate, if you look at this diagram, you can see that units are building up inventory, because as units are arriving, but the process is not ready to accept these new flow units.
Trường hợp thứ nhất, khi tốc độ đến vượt tỉ lệ xử lý, nhìn vào biểu đồ này, bạn có thể thấy các đơn vị đang làm tăng lượng hàng tồn kho, bởi vì các đơn vị tiếp tục đến nhưng quá trình xử lý không sẵn sàng để tiếp nhận những đơn vị mới được đưa vào này.
So it's going to build up. So in this case, The output of the process of throughput rate
Do đó tồn kho sẽ tăng lên. Trong trường hợp này, đầu ra của quá trình của tốc độ thông lượng là 9
100% untilized, which means if you have the arrival rate exceeding your process rate, here is no downtime for that process
100% được sử dụng, nghĩa là nếu tốc độ đến vượt tốc độ xử lý thì sẽ không có thời gian nghỉ cho cả quá trình.
It's been used 100% capacity. And it's high arrival rate is going to increases work in process inventory. Because if you want an unit going through your arriving, waiting for the process to handle it and the process it's just slow. It can not handle all of those units. So when we're thinking about increasing throughput rate of a process, we always have to consider how quickly the process can handle these new units
100% công suất đã được sử dụng, và tốc độ đến cao sẽ làm tăng công việc đối với xử lý hàng tồn kho. Bởi vì muốn một đơn vị qua xử lý, bạn phải chờ cho quá trình xử lý nó và làm cho quá trình chậm đi. Không thể xử lý tất cả các đơn vị đó. Vì thế khi nghĩ đến việc tăng tốc độ lưu thông của một quá trình, ta phải luôn cân nhắc đến thời gian quá trình có thể xử lý các đơn vị mới này.
The second situation is the arrival rate is less than process rate.
Trường hợp thứ hai là tốc độ đến thấp hơn tốc độ xử lý.
And here you that we have almost no build-up inventory in practice. None here. And on average, the process is waiting for the arrival of units. Now we can get some small inventory build-up because there is variability in arrival of units.
Và trường hợp này trong thực tiễn hầu như không làm tăng lượng hàng tòn kho. Và thông thường quá trình phải chở đợi cho các đơn vị khác đến. Bây giờ chúng ta có thể tạo ra một lượng tồn kho nhỏ bởi vì sự biến thiên trong việc nhập vào các đơn vị.
Remember when we talk about
Hãy nhớ rằng khi nói đến
And also variability in processing of the units. So in this case, when the arrival rate is less than process rate,
vậy nên trong trường hợp này, khi tỉ lệ đến thấp hơn tỉ lệ xử lý
then average throughput rate is going to be controlled by the arrival rate of the units. So this meansthe output of process is limited to the arrival rate. And average utilization of the process itself is going to be less than 100%. 'Cos there will be period of time when the process is waiting for units
thì tốc độ lưu thông trung bình sẽ bị chi phối bởi tốc độ đến của các đơn vị. Nghĩa là đầu ra của quá trình bị giới hạn bởi tốc độ đến. Công suất trung bình của quá trình sẽ thấp hơn 100%. Bởi vì sẽ có một khoảng thời thời quá trình chờ các đơn vị đến để xử lý.
to arrive. And our work in process inventory is low or non-existent because the process is faster than the units can arrive. The third situation when arrival rate equals to process rate
Và công việc của chúng ta trong xử lý hàng tồn kho là ít hoặc không có bởi vì quá trình xử lý nhanh hơn các đơn vị đến. Trường hợp thứ 3 là khi tốc độ đến bằng tố độ xử lý
Well, here, it's similar to that of the previous situation when the arrival rate is less than process rate
Cũng giống như trường hợp trước khi tốc độ đến thấp hơn tốc độ xử lý
But although the arrival rate and the process rate is the same, there is some variability in units coming. So we can have some small inventory build-up and there can be times when the process is waiting. So the arrival rate equals to process rate, which equals to throughput rate
Nhưng mặc dù tốc độ đến và tốc độ xử lý là như nhau, vẵn có sự biến thiên trong các đơn vị đến. Cho nên chúng ta có thể tạo ra một lượng nhỏ tồn kho và có thể có lúc quá trình xử lý phải chờ. Vậy nên tốc độ vào bằng tốc độ xử lý, bằng với tốc độ lưu thông
So the ouput is limited to capability of the process itself.
cho nên đầu ra bị giới hạn bởi khả năng của quá trình xử lý.
And here our capacity utilization can be just about 100%, which means that process is working almost all of the time and we may get some work in process inventory increases over time due to variability of arrival and process rates themselves. So when we thinking about throughput of a process,
Mức sử dụng công năng có thể là 100%, nghĩa là quá trình làm việc hầu như hết quỹ thời gian và chúng ta có thể sẽ phải xử lý tồn kho tăng lên do sự biến thiên của tốc độ đến và tố độ xử lý. Vậy nên khi nghỉ đến thông lượng của một quá trình,
remember you have to consider the arrival rate and the process rate itself . If the arrival rate exceed than the process, then the process is controlling the throughput rate. If the arrival rate is less than the process, then it is the arrival rate that is controlling the throughput rate. Thanks for watching. I'll see you next time.
nhớ phải cân nhắc đén tốc đọ đến và tốc độ xử lý của nó. Nếu tốc độ đến vượt quá tốc độ xử lý thì tốc độ xử lý chi phối tốc độ lưu thông. Nếu ttoocs độ đến nhỏ hơn tốc độ xử lý thì tốc độ đến chi phối tốc độ lưu thông. Cảm ơn các bạn đã xem. Gặp lại các bạn sau nhé.